TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
（バルサ）まきの真ん中から
目を離すんじゃないよ
Don't take your eyes off
the center of the wood.
（チャグム）えい！ 痛っ…
Ow!
（バルサ）ハハッ
そうやって体で覚えるしかないね
You'll just have to learn by
actually trying your hand at it.
（男の子１）ほら 行くぞ！
Wait for me!
（男の子２）待ってよ！
（男の子１）遅いんだよ！
Wait for me!
Walk faster!
They all seem to be
excited about something.
（チャグム）なんだか
みんな ウキウキしているようだな
Yes, it's because the Summer
Solstice Festival is coming up soon.
ああ もうすぐ夏至祭だからね
祭り？
Festival?
Around here, they say you
can tell how many days are left...
（バルサ）ここらじゃ
襟元のはだけ具合で―
祭りまでの日にちが
分かるって言われてんのさ
...until the festival by how much the
villagers have loosened their collars.
ふーん
Episode 12
The
Summer
Solstice
Festival
さっきの人たち―
The people who passed by earlier
were carrying rather large torches.
ずいぶん大きな たいまつを
担いでいたけど―
What will they be used for?
あれは 何に使うんだ？
l guess they'll be used when
they go from house to house...
多分 祭りのときに
一軒一軒を回って―
...to light the bonfires
during the festival.
かがり火をともすために
使うんだろうね
（チャグム）ふーん
Oh, l see! Those were the lights
that we could see from the palace!
あっ そうか
宮殿から見えていた明かりは
それだ
At court, we celebrate the Founding
Day Festival at the spring equinox.
宮では 春分に建国祭をやるんだ
lt commemorates the victory over
the water demon by my holy ancestor...
聖祖トルガル帝と八武人(はちぶじん)が
水妖(すいよう)を倒し―
...Torugaru, and his Warriors Eight,
and the founding of Shin-Yogo.
新ヨゴ皇国を建てたのを
記念する お祭り
聞いたことがあるね
l've heard about it before.
l always wondered
why the farmers...
でも なんで農民も同じときに―
かがり火を燃やさないのだろうと
思っていたけど―
...didn't light their
bonfires at the same time.
But since they're busy
planting rice at the start of spring...
春先は 田植えで忙しいから―
夏至に それを
やるようになったんだな きっと
...they began doing it at the summer
solstice instead. That must be it.
l see... You may be right.
なるほど そうかもね
毎年 夏至の日は 帝(みかど)や兄上と
星読みの塔から都を眺めるんだ
Every year on the summer solstice,
l would look down on the city...
...from the star tower with
the mikado and my brother.
すると 家々に ともされた火が―
The fires lit at all the houses
would make it look as if...
...the river of heaven had
come down to flow across the land.
まるで 大地を流れる
天の川のように見えるんだ
Do you want to
go back to your old life?
そのころの暮らしに戻りたいかい？
いや 戻りたくなんかないよ
No, l don't want to go back to that.
Hey! Chagum!
（ガキ大将）おーい チャグム！
（バルサ）うん？
We're all gonna go practice lucha!
（ガキ大将）これから
みんなで ルチャをやるんだ
Lucha? You mean the martial art?
（チャグム）ルチャ？
格闘技のルチャのことか？
（ガキ大将）他に何がある？
ls there any other lucha?
祭りに向けて稽古するんだ
We're going to practice
for the festival!
Come practice with us!
お前も来いよ！
祭りの日に
ルチャ大会があるのさ
There's a lucha tournament
on the day of the festival.
（チャグム）ふーん
（バルサ）行ってきなよ
Go ahead.
Let's go!
行こう！
Come on!
（ガキ大将）おーい！
Why are you all bowing
with your eyes closed?
なんで みんな 目をつぶりながら
おじぎをするんだ？
What do you mean, why?
なんでって… あっ！
これはトルガル帝とともに
水妖を倒した―
These are the statues of
the legendary Warriors Eight...
...who fought alongside Mikado
Torugaru to slay the water demon!
伝説の八武人の石像だぞ！
lf you look them in the eye,
you'll be struck blind!
そんなに まじまじと見たら
目が つぶれるだろ！
That makes no sense.
それは おかしい
Commoners are only struck blind
looking at members of the royal family...
平民が見ると 目がつぶれると
言われているのは―
...who are descendants of
their sacred ancestor Torugaru.
聖祖トルガル帝の
子孫である皇族だけだ
（ガキ大将）えっ… そうなのか？
ls he right?
（コヒョイ）えっ？
（ノボ）さあ？
l don't know...
（チャグム）それに
その皇族も 見ただけで―
Besides, no one has ever gone blind
just by looking at the royal family.
目がつぶれるなんてことは
なかった
What did you just say?
（コヒョイ）
えっ… 何言ってんだ！ お前
（ノボ）罰当たりな！
You're going to get it!
（ガキ大将）お前 まさか―
Wait, are you saying that you've
actually looked at one of the royal family?
皇族を見たことがあるとでも
言うのか？
No, l only meant...
いや それは…
You over there, what are you doing?
（ヤーサム）
お前ら 何やってんだよ？
Who is that, anyway?
何だ？ あいつ
（ヤーサム）
これから このヤーサム様が―
The mighty Yarsam is about to start
practicing for the lucha tournament...
ルチャ大会に向けて
稽古するから お前ら相手しろ
...so l want you to fight me!
（ガキ大将）お前 ロタ人か？
（ヤーサム）見れば分かるだろうが
Are you from Rota?
Can't you tell by looking at me?
Rota?
ロタ人？
（女の子）
夏至祭があるから来たんだ
He's here for the
Summer Solstice Festival.
お祭りになると―
Whenever there's a festival, traveling
merchants come from far and wide.
あちこちから
旅商人が集まってくるんだよ
Oh, he's a merchant's son.
旅商人の子供か
What's the matter?
Let's get started!
どうした？ 早くやろうぜ
なんで 流れ者のお前に そんなこと
言われなくちゃならないんだ？
Why should we take orders
from a drifter like you?
lf you need our help so badly,
bow your head and ask politely!
そんなにやりたきゃ
頭を下げて お前が頼めよ
Why should l have to bow down
to a bunch of Yogo kids?
なんで俺様が お前らヨゴ人に
頭を下げなきゃならないんだ？
What did you say?
何だと？
Get him, big brother!
Make that foreigner sorry!
やっちゃえ！ お兄ちゃん
そんな よそ者 やっつけちゃえ！
Right! Get him!
（コヒョイ）そうだ そうだ！
（ノボ）やっちゃえ！
Beat him up!
This should be good.
面白(おもしれ)え
じゃ お前はルチャでこい
Okay, you come
at me with your lucha.
俺はロタの国技
ポラックでいくからな
l'll be using porakku,
Rota's national martial art.
俺が勝ったら
お前たち全員 俺の子分だからな
lf l win, all of you
have to be my minions!
負けるかよ
No way am l going to lose.
先に ひざから上が
地面についたほうが負けだからな
First one who touches the ground
with anything above the knees loses!
Agreed?
いいな？
始め！
Begin!
おら！ おら！
Take that! Take that!
Why you...
（ガキ大将）この！
Ow! That hurts!
Big brother!
（女の子）お兄ちゃん！
ほら さっきまでの元気は
どうしたんだ？
Not so tough now, are you?
Round and round...
...we go!
おーらよ！
（ガキ大将）うわっ！
（女の子）お兄ちゃん！
Big brother!
That was pathetic.
ぶざまだな
何すんだ！ ひどいじゃないか！
What do you think you're doing!
That's so mean!
そこまですることは ないだろ
You didn't have to take it that far!
Don't give me any of that whining.
何 甘っちょろいこと言ってんだ
l've won, so that means
you're all under my power now.
（ヤーサム）これで お前ら
みんな 俺の子分ってことだな
フン！
こんな へたれ連中を
子分にしたって しょうがねえか
But you're such a bunch of losers...
lt doesn't seem worth it!
ヨゴのガキが これだけ
腰抜けぞろいだってことは―
lf the kids in Yogo are
all weaklings like you...
...that must mean the mikado of this
country must be a real weakling too!
この国の帝も
どうせ腰抜けなんだろうな！
帝と俺たちのこととは関係ない！
The mikado has
nothing to do with us!
帝が腰抜けだと言ったことを
取り消せ！
Take back what you said about
the mikado being a weakling!
Yeah!
そうだ！
帝のことを悪く言うなんて許せない
You can't insult the mikado!
We won't let you.
あん？ 何言ってんだ 負け犬どもが
What are you
talking about, you losers?
俺と勝負しろ
You're going to fight me.
lf l win, you have to take back
what you said about the mikado.
俺が勝ったら
帝の悪口を取り消すんだ
（ヤーサム）ふざけるな
Don't mess with me. Why should
l do as my own minion tells me?
なんで 子分の言うことを
聞かなきゃならないんだ
l'm no minion of yours!
俺は子分なんかじゃない
Don't do it, Chagum!
やめな！ チャグム
お兄ちゃんが負けたんだ
あんたに勝てるわけないよ
Not even my brother could beat him!
You don't stand a chance!
l don't mind fighting you,
but there's no fun in fighting a weakling.
勝負をしてやるのはいいが―
弱いヤツと
ただ勝負しても面白くないからな
じゃ こうしよう
Let's do it this way then.
l'll give you a one-day reprieve.
お前に１日の猶予をやろう
夏至祭の本番で勝負だ
We'll fight in the tournament
on the day of the festival.
On the off chance that l do happen
to lose, l'll give in to your demand.
そこで 万が一
俺が負けた場合には―
お前の要求を聞いてやる
その代わり―
On the other hand, if you lose...
お前が負けたら みんなの前で
ナメクジを食べてもらうからな
...you have to eat slugs
in front of everyone, all right?
You're on!
分かった
でっかいナメクジ
見つけておくからな
l'm going to find some
big, juicy slugs for you!
Make sure you come
with an empty stomach!
せいぜい腹すかせてこいよ
（チャグム）なあ バルサ
（バルサ）うん？
Say, Balsa.
Have you ever traveled to Rota?
（チャグム）バルサは
ロタに行ったことがあるか？
Yes. Why do you ask?
（バルサ）ああ なんでだい？
l met a boy from Rota today.
今日 ロタ人の子に会った
体が大きくて 気性が荒いんだ
そいつ
He was big and foul-tempered.
ロタ人ってのは おおむね そうさ
Most people from Rota are like that.
For people as large as they are,
they can be surprisingly touchy.
体が大きいわりに
神経質なところがあるからね
Many different races call it home...
あそこは
いろんな民族が集まってるし―
貧富の差も激しい
...and there's a huge gap
between rich and poor.
それで
ギスギスした性格のヤツが多いのさ
That's why there are so many people
there with high-strung personalities.
ln contrast, the Yogo
people are easygoing...
それに反して
ヨゴ人は おおらかだから―
ロタ人は余計に
イライラするってわけさ
...which can get on
a Rotan's nerves all the more.
Ah, l see.
（チャグム）そうなのか
Actually, l'm supposed to fight
this Rotan boy in a lucha match.
実は そのロタ人と ルチャの勝負を
することになったんだ
But he uses a martial art called
porakku, and he's very good at it.
でも相手は ポラックっていう
武術を持っていて―
すごく強いんだ
へえー
Do you think there's
any way that l might beat him?
何か勝てる方法はないかな？
Porakku is a martial art developed out
of unarmed combat on the battlefield.
ポラックは
戦場での体術を元に発展した武術だ
それに比べると ルチャは
農民の遊びの延長だから―
ln comparison, lucha is just
an extension of farmers' horseplay...
ちょいと難しい勝負だね
...so the odds aren't
really in your favor.
でも 土俵から
出せばいいってんなら勝機はある
But if you just have to throw him from
the ring, you do have a chance to win.
Really?
（チャグム）本当？
You'll need a lot of courage
and a little skill to pull it off, though.
かなりの勇気と
ちょいとしたコツが必要だけどね
それで
その勝負は いつやるんだい？
So, when is this match
going to be held?
夏至祭だ
The Solstice Festival.
（バルサ）そいつは残念だったね
l'm sorry to hear that.
その勝負 今回は諦めな
You'll have to let this one go.
私らは 祭りには行けないのさ
We can't go to the festival.
Why not?
なぜだ？
祭りってのは 大勢の人が集まる
Lots of people go to festivals.
夜店も出れば テキヤもやって来る
Where there are night stalls, there
will also be shady street peddlers.
And that means that all sorts of shady
characters, people who can't normally...
…ってことは いつもは 太陽の下に
出てこられないような―
...show their faces in broad daylight,
will also be emerging from all over.
裏の人間が あちこちから
集まってくるってことだろ？
私たちは
本来 ここにいないはずの人間だ
You and l aren't
supposed to still be alive.
Living the way we do here
won't raise any red flags...
ふだんどおり暮らしている分には
何ともないが―
祭りとなると
どんな人間が見ているか分からない
...but at a festival, there's no
telling who might be watching.
だから おとなしく
家の中にいなくちゃならないのさ
So we need to be inconspicuous
and stay in the house that night.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
Good morning.
（チャグム）おはよう
（バルサ）おはよう
Wash up, and then let's stack up
the firewood we chopped yesterday.
顔を洗ったら―
飯の前に 昨日割ったまきを
積み上げてしまおう
We might not be able to go to the festival,
but we can at least light a bonfire!
祭りには行けないが
かがり火は たこうじゃないか
Sure.
Balsa, you said yesterday that
l had a chance if l only needed to...
ねえ バルサ
昨日 土俵から出すだけだったら
なんとかなるって言っただろ？
...throw him from
the ring, remember?
What did you mean by that?
あれって どういうこと？
まだ そのことを考えていたのかい
（チャグム）うん
You're still thinking about that?
Yes.
Well, l suppose l can tell you if you
promise you won't go to the festival.
まあ 祭りには行かないと
約束できるなら―
教えてやってもいいけどね
Chagum, do you know what
makes the waterwheel turn?
チャグム
なんで水車が回るのか分かるかい？
（バルサ）水は チョロチョロと
少ししか流れていないだろ？
There's only a slow trickle
of water flowing past it, right?
Why do you think it is...
水車は とても重いのに―
なぜ これだけの水で
勢いよく回すことができると思う？
...that so little water can keep
such a heavy wheel turning steadily?
重たいものでも
一度 弾みさえつければ―
lt's because once you get
something moving, even if it's heavy...
...you can keep it moving
with just a small amount of force.
あとは
小さな力で動かすことができるんだ
そして いったん動き始めれば―
And once it starts moving, the heavier
an object is, the greater its momentum...
重いものほど 勢いがついて
あとは簡単に回り続ける
...and the easier it is
to keep it moving.
肝心なのは 最初の弾みを
どうやって つけるかさ
The trick is figuring out
how to give it that initial kick.
（村人たち）
火 食らえ！ 火 食らえ！
Light the fires!
（村人たち）
火 食らえ！ 火 食らえ！
All that firewood we chopped...
We're going to use almost all of it!
（チャグム）
あれだけ割った まきを―
ほとんど全部 使ってしまうんだな
そうだね
Yes, we are.
（村人たち）火 食らえ！
Light the fires!
And here they are.
（バルサ）来たね
（村人たち）火 食らえ！
And here they are.
Light the fires!
火 食らえ！ 火 食らえ！
Since we can't go to the festival,
let's treat ourselves to a special meal.
祭りに行けない分
うまい物(もん)でも食べよう
まきが足らなくなるかもしれない
We might run out of firewood.
Split a few more logs, will you?
少し割っておくれ
（チャグム）分かった
All right.
（男性１）何やってんだ！ おら！
Come on!
l'm next!
（男性２）次は俺だ！
Chagum, it's almost time to eat.
（バルサ）
チャグム そろそろ飯にするよ
l knew it. He went anyway...
やっぱり出かけやがったか
What would Jiguro do
in a situation like this?
ジグロだったら
こんなとき どうしたっけね
（男性１）今年は
あなたには かないませんでした
You had us completely
outmatched this year.
Anyway, let's have
a toast to your victory.
（男性２）まあ
ここは ひとつ １杯
l knew my old man was tough...
（ヤーサム）
やっぱ 親父(おやじ)は強いや
あいつ とうとう来なかったな
Looks like your friend
decided not to show up.
So do you want to
eat these for him?
お前ら 代わりに食べるか？
ほら 遠慮すんな うん？
Dig in!
Don't be shy!
Oh, so now you finally
decide to show your face?
なんだ 今頃 来やがったよ
わざわざ
ナメクジを食いに来たか？
You didn't want to miss out
on your slug treat?
l haven't lost just yet.
まだ負けと決まったわけじゃない
（ヤーサム）
もう大会は終わっちまったぞ
The tournament is over.
But the ring is still here.
でも 土俵は残ってる
それとも ホントは
俺と勝負するのが怖いのか？
Or maybe the truth is that
you're afraid to take me on?
そこまで言うなら やってやる
l'll be glad to fight you
if you're going to talk like that.
Don't come crying to me later!
あとで後悔して泣くなよ
さっさと終わらせるとするか
l guess l won't draw
this out. l'll just end it.
Come and get me, slug boy!
かかってこいよ  ナメクジちゃん
（チャグム）
お前こそ 体が でかいだけで―
Your only asset is your size.
You yourself are as slow as a slug.
ナメクジ並みに とろそうだ
口だけじゃないなら
早いとこ そいつを見せてみろよ
lf you aren't all talk, hurry up
and show me what you have!
He's going to get himself killed!
あいつ 殺されちゃうよ
何だと！
What did you say to me!
l was going let you off
with just eating a slug...
ナメクジだけで許してやろうと
思ったが 痛い目 見せてやる！
...but l'm going
to make you hurt now!
He did it! Chagum won!
やった！ チャグムの勝ちだ！
（ガキ大将）おお！
Right!
Chagum won!
（女の子）チャグムの勝ちだ！
何だ？ 今のは
Hey, what was that?
汚(きたね)えぞ！
That was a dirty move!
You left the ring. You lose!
（ガキ大将）
土俵から出たんだ お前の負けだ
That's not what happened!
l didn't lose!
今のは違う 俺は負けてねえ！
Now, take back what
you said about the mikado.
帝について言ったことを
取り消してくれ
Forget it.
嫌だね
お前は ひきょうだ
だから帝も ひきょう者だ！
You cheated. That means
the mikado is a cheater too.
That's not what we agreed on!
約束が違うぞ！
You little bastard!
この野郎！
（ガキ大将）チャグム！
Chagum!
（ヤーサムの父）
ヤーサム もう よせ
Yarsam!
Let it go, Son. ln lucha,
you lose if you leave the ring.
ルチャってのは
土俵から出たら負けなんだ
Conceding the match is the honorable
thing for a man of Rota to do here.
ここは 勝ちを譲ってやるのも
立派なロタの男だ
今年は俺が優勝したんだ
胸を張れ
l won the tournament this year.
Hold your head high.
ln this village, there are no
adults stronger than l am...
この村に 大人で
俺より強いヤツはいないし―
子供では お前が１番だ
そのことに変わりはない
...and no child is stronger than you.
Nothing can change that.
ちくしょう
Damn it...
（ヤーサムの父）さあ 行くぞ
（チャグム）違う
Come on, let's go.
But that's not...
（バルサ）ちょっと待ちな
Just a minute.
Conceding the match
isn't the issue here.
勝ちを譲られたって困るんだよ
Your boy has to keep up
his end of the agreement.
あんたんとこの子には ちゃんと
約束を守ってもらわなきゃね
Agreement? What agreement?
約束？ 何だ それは
l-l don't know what
she's talking about!
し… 知らねえよ
知らんそうだ
言いがかりは やめてくれ
He says he made no promise.
Please stop making false accusations.
So the father gets
to rule on his son's disputes?
子供のケンカを
親父がジャッジするってか
ls that the honorable thing
for a man of Rota to do?
それが
立派なロタの男のやることかい？
That being the case,
why don't we parents settle this?
だったら
親同士で決着をつけようじゃないか
勝ったほうが正しいってことで
子供の言うことを認める
Whoever wins is in the right,
and we'll abide by what that child says.
What is she talking about? Let's go.
何だよ それ
行こうぜ
うちは父ちゃんがいないからね
私が相手になるよ
This boy doesn't have a father,
so l'll be the one fighting you.
何？
What?
Women are barred from
lucha matches, but l'm a Rotan.
ルチャは女人禁制だが
俺はロタ人だしな
l myself have no
problem fighting you...
俺は別に かまわないが
私もカンバル人だ 決まりだね
And l'm from Kanbal.
We have a deal then.
私が勝ったら
約束は守ってもらうよ
lf l win, your son is
going to keep his word.
あんたには
あとで たっぷり言うことがあるよ
We're going to have a long talk
once this is over. Wait right there.
そこで待ってな
l'm not going to dodge
at the last second...
私は いなしたりしないから
本気で かかってきな
...so feel free to give it all you've got.
いけ！
そんな女 ひねり上げちゃえ！
Get in there! Lift her off her feet!
（ヤーサム）親父！
Father!
親父 今のは
女だから手 抜いてやったんだろ？
Father, you went easy on her
because she's a woman, right?
Right? That's it, isn't it?
なっ？ そうだよな？
That is no ordinary woman...
あの女 ただ者(もん)じゃない
She didn't win by some fluke
or because l held back.
今のは 俺が手を抜いたんでも
まぐれでもない
lf l fought her ten times,
she would win all ten matches.
10回やっても 10回あいつが勝つ
お前 約束ってのが何か知らねえが
急いで謝ってこい！
l don't know what you promised,
but apologize, and be quick about it!
But...
そんな…
誰かに見られてたら―
lf we'd been spotted, we wouldn't
be able to live like this anymore.
今までの暮らしは
もうできないんだ
You understand that, right?
分かるだろ？
ごめんなさい
l'm sorry.
（バルサ）まあ 騒ぎを
大きくしちまったのは私だけどね
Well, l was the one
who made matters worse.
But l was the one who
started it all by breaking my word.
でも
最初に約束を破ったのは俺だから
お前が あそこまでして
戦いに行った気持ち―
l'm sure that your parents
would have been proud...
あんたの親としては
うれしかったろうよ
...that you went
to such lengths to fight for them.
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
Someone has realized
that Balsa is still alive.
A wild beast born of
Balsa's karma... her past deeds.
Next time,
"Neither Human nor Tiger."
Episode 13
Neither Human nor Tiger
Deep within Balsa, something
that had lain dormant is roused...